<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The churle and the byrde</title>
            <title>Chorle and the birde</title>
            <author>Lydgate, John, 1370?-1451?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1565</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 21 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06549</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17014</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109661</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845308</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845308</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10200</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06549)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10200)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 429:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The churle and the byrde</title>
                  <title>Chorle and the birde</title>
                  <author>Lydgate, John, 1370?-1451?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Lothburi ouer against Sainct Margarytes church by me Wyllam Copland,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprented at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[ca. 1565]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By John Lydgate.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name and place of publication from colophon; publication date estimated by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>With a title-page woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of a photostat of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10200:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10200:1"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The Churle and the Byrde.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of man and bird</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:10200:2"/>
            <lg>
               <l>PRoblemes of olde lykeneſſe and fygure</l>
               <l>Which proued ben, fructuous of ſilence</l>
               <l>And haue auctorites, grounded in ſcripture</l>
               <l>By reſemblaunce, of notable aparaunce</l>
               <l>with moralities, concludynge on prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</l>
               <l>Lyke as the byble reherſeth by wrytynge</l>
               <l>How trees ſomtyme choſe them a kynge.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Fyrſte in theyr choyſe, they named Olyue</l>
               <l>To rayne amonge them, iudicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth expreſſe</l>
               <l>But he hymſefle gan excuſe blyue</l>
               <l>That they myght nat forſake the fatneſſe</l>
               <l>Nor the fygge tre, her amorous ſwetnes</l>
               <l>Nor the vyne tre, his holſome freſſhe corage</l>
               <l>which gyueth comforte, to all maner of age</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſemblable poytes laureate</l>
               <l>By darke parables full conuenient</l>
               <l>Fayne that byrdes and beeſtes of eſtate</l>
               <l>As royall Egles, and lyons by aſſent</l>
               <l>Sent out writtes to holde a paralyment</l>
               <l>And made the crye, breuely for to ſay</l>
               <l>So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to haue lorde ſhyp, and ſome to obeye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Egles in the ayre, hyeſt to take theyr flyght</l>
               <l>Power of lyons, on the grounde is ſene</l>
               <l>Cedre amonge trees, hygheſt in ſyght</l>
               <l>The laurell of nature, is aye grene</l>
               <l>Of floures all Flora, aye goddeſſe and quene</l>
               <l>Thus in all thynges, there ben dyuerſyti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s</l>
               <l>Churle &amp; byrde.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10200:2"/>Some of eſtate, and ſome of lowe degrees.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Poytes wryte, wonderfull lykeneſſe</l>
               <l>And vnder couert, kepe them ſelfe full cloſe</l>
               <l>They take beeſtes, and foules to wytneſſe</l>
               <l>Of whoſe ſayenges, fables fyrſt a roſe</l>
               <l>And here I caſt on my purpoſe</l>
               <l>Out of frenche, a tale to tranſlate</l>
               <l>which in a pamflete, I ſaw and redde but late</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This tale, which I make mencyon</l>
               <l>In groſe reherſeth playnly to declare</l>
               <l>The great prouerbe, payed for the raunſon</l>
               <l>Of a lytell byrde, taken in a ſnare</l>
               <l>wonderfull deſyrous, to eſcape out of care</l>
               <l>Of myn auctor folowynge the proceſſe</l>
               <l>So as it fell, in ordre I ſhall you expreſſe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Somtyme there dwelled in a ſmall vylage</l>
               <l>As myn anctor maketh mencyon</l>
               <l>A churle, which had luſt and corage</l>
               <l>within hym ſelfe, by dyligent trauayle</l>
               <l>To aray his garden, with notable aparayle</l>
               <l>Of length and brede, in lyke ſquare and longe</l>
               <l>Hedged and dytched, to make it ſure and ſtronge</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All the alayes, were mayde playne with ſande</l>
               <l>The benches couered, which newe turues grene</l>
               <l>with the ſwete yerbes, and condytes at hande</l>
               <l>Than welled vp agaynſt the ſonne ſhynynge</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10200:3"/>Lyke vnto ſyluer, or any chriſtall clere</l>
               <l>The byrbyll wawes, in theyr vp boylynge</l>
               <l>Rounde as byrrall, theyr beames out ſhyuynge.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In myddes of the garden, ſtode a freſſhe laurere</l>
               <l>Theron a byrde ſyngynge day and nyght</l>
               <l>with ſhyni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge fethers, bryghter than the golde wyr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>which with her ſonge, made heuy hertes lyght</l>
               <l>that her to beholde, it was an heuenly ſyght</l>
               <l>Now towarde euyn, and in the dawnynge</l>
               <l>She dyd her payne mooſt amerouſly to ſynge</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Eſperous enforced her corage</l>
               <l>towarde euyn, whan phebus went to the weſt</l>
               <l>Amonge the braunches, to take her aduauntage</l>
               <l>To ſynge her complaynte, and than to go to reſt</l>
               <l>And at the ryſynge of the quene Alceſt</l>
               <l>to ſynge agayne, as it were her deu</l>
               <l>Early on the morow, the day after to ſalue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>It was a very heuenly melody</l>
               <l>Euen and morow to heare the byrdes ſonge</l>
               <l>And the ſwete ſugred ermony</l>
               <l>with vncouth warbles and tunes draw alonge</l>
               <l>That all the garden, of the noyſe tonge</l>
               <l>Tyll on the morowe, whan tytan dyd ſhyne clere</l>
               <l>the byrde was trapped, and caught in a pantere</l>
               <l>¶ The churle was glad, that he y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> byrde had take</l>
               <l>Mery of chere, of loke and vyſage</l>
               <l>And in all haſt, he caſt for to make</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10200:3"/>Within his houſe, a lytell prety cage</l>
               <l>And with her ſonge, to reioyſe his corage</l>
               <l>tyll at the laſt, the cely byrde a brayde</l>
               <l>And ſoberly to the churle ſhe ſayd</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I am take and ſtande vnder daungere</l>
               <l>Holden ſtrayte, that I may nat fle</l>
               <l>A due my ſonge, my luſty notes clere</l>
               <l>Now haue I loſte my lyberte</l>
               <l>Now am I thrall, that ſomtyme was fre</l>
               <l>And truſt me well, whyle I ſtande in diſtriſſe</l>
               <l>I can nat ſynge, nor make no gladneſſe?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And though my cage forged were of golde</l>
               <l>And the pynacles, of byrrall and chryſtall</l>
               <l>I remembre a prouerbe of olde</l>
               <l>who leſeth his fredome he leſeth all</l>
               <l>For I had leauer, vpon a braunche ſmall</l>
               <l>Merely ſynge, amonge the leaues grene</l>
               <l>Than in a cage of ſyluer bryght and ſhyne</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sothe and pryſon, haue none accordaunce</l>
               <l>Troweſt thou I wyle ſynge in pryſon</l>
               <l>Nay, for ſonge procedeth of ioy and pleſaunce</l>
               <l>And pryſon cauſeth doth and diſtruction.</l>
               <l>Redynge of letters maketh no mery ſounde</l>
               <l>Or who ſhulde be mery or iocounde</l>
               <l>Agaynſt his wyll that lyeth in chaynes bounde</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What auayleth a Lyon to be a kynge</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10200:4"/>To be ſhyt vp in a towre of ſtone</l>
               <l>Or an Egle vnder ſtreyte kepynge</l>
               <l>Calle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> kynge of foules euery<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hone</l>
               <l>Fye on lordſhyp, whan lyberte is gone</l>
               <l>Anſwere hereto, and let it not aſtarte</l>
               <l>who ſyngeth merely, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſyngeth not at the her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But and thou wylt reioyce of my ſyngynge</l>
               <l>Suffre me to go fre from all daunger</l>
               <l>And euery day in the greue mornynge</l>
               <l>I wyll repayre vnto the la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rere</l>
               <l>And merely ſynge with luſty note clere</l>
               <l>Vnder the chamber, or a fore thyne hall</l>
               <l>Euery ſeaſon, whan thou lyſt me to call.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To be ſhyt vp and pynned vnder drede</l>
               <l>Nothynge accordeth to my nature</l>
               <l>Thoughe I were fedd with mylke &amp; waſtell brede</l>
               <l>And ſwete curdes brought to my paſture</l>
               <l>yet had I leuer to do my buſy cure</l>
               <l>Erly on the morow to ſcrapt in the wall</l>
               <l>To fynde my dyner, amonge the wormes ſmall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The labourer is gladder at the plough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Erly on morowe to fede hym with bacon</l>
               <l>Than ſome man is, that hath treaſour ynough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>And of all dei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ties plente and foyſon</l>
               <l>And no fredome with his poſſeſſyon</l>
               <l>To go at large, but as a bere at a ſtake</l>
               <l>To paſſe his bondes yf he leue take.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10200:4"/>
               <l>Take this anſwere for a ſhorte concluſyon</l>
               <l>to ſynge in pryſon thou ſhalte me nat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſtreyne</l>
               <l>Tyll I haue fredome in wodes vp and downe</l>
               <l>to flye at large, on boughe roughe and playne</l>
               <l>And of reaſon thou ſhuldeſt not diſdayne</l>
               <l>Of my deſyre, but laughe and haue good game</l>
               <l>But he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is a churle, wolde eche ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were the ſame</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ well quod the churle, ſyth it wyll nat be</l>
               <l>That I deſyre as by thi talkynge</l>
               <l>Maugry thi will, thou ſhalte choſe one of thre</l>
               <l>within a cage merely to ſynge</l>
               <l>Or to the kechyn I ſhall thy body brynge</l>
               <l>Plucke thy fethers, that ben bryght and clere</l>
               <l>And after roſt or bake the to my ſopere</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>well quod the byrde, as to reaſon I ſay not nay</l>
               <l>thouchynge my ſonge, a full anſwere thou haſt</l>
               <l>And whan my fethers ben plucked away</l>
               <l>Yf I be roſte and baken in paſt</l>
               <l>On me thou ſhalte haue but a ſmall repaſte</l>
               <l>But and yf thou wylte worke after my cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſayle</l>
               <l>By me mayſt thou haue great auayle</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yf thou wylte vnto my reaſon aſſent</l>
               <l>And ſuffre me to go fre from pryſon</l>
               <l>without raunſom, or any other rent</l>
               <l>I ſhall the gyue a notable guerdon</l>
               <l>Thre great wyſdome<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, accordynge to reaſon</l>
               <l>More of value, take hede what I profer</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10200:5"/>Than all thy golde that is ſhyt in thy cofer</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Truſt me well, I wyll the nat diſceyue</l>
               <l>well quod the churle, tell on let ſe</l>
               <l>Nay quod the byrde, thou muſt afore conceyue</l>
               <l>who that ſhall teche of reaſon muſt go fre</l>
               <l>It ſytteth, a mayſter to haue his lyberte</l>
               <l>And at large to teche his leſſon</l>
               <l>Haue me not in ſuſpecte I meane no treaſon</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>well quod the churle I holde me content</l>
               <l>I truſt thy promyſe which thou makeſt me</l>
               <l>The byrde flewe forth, the chorle was of aſſent</l>
               <l>And toke her flyght, vnto the laurer tre</l>
               <l>than thought ſhe, now ſtand I fre</l>
               <l>with no panters I caſt nat a I my lyfe</l>
               <l>Nor with lyme twygges, any more to ſtryue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He is a fole that ſcaped is daungere</l>
               <l>Broken his fetters, and fled out of pryſon</l>
               <l>To reſorte, for the brent chylde dredeth fyre</l>
               <l>Eche man beware of wyſdome and reaſon</l>
               <l>Of ſugre ſtrewed, whiche hydeth falſe poyſon</l>
               <l>There is no poyſon venim ſo per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llꝰ of ſharpeneſſe</l>
               <l>As is, whan it hathe of tryacle a lykeneſſe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Who dredeth no peryll, in peryll he ſhall fall</l>
               <l>Smothe waters ben oftentymes depe</l>
               <l>The quayle pype can moſt falſly call</l>
               <l>tyll the quayle vnder the net doth crepe</l>
               <l>A blerecyed fouler, truſt not though he wepe</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10200:5"/>Eſchewe his tombe, of wepynge take no hede</l>
               <l>That ſymple byrdes can nype vy the hede.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And I that now ſuch daungere am eſcaped</l>
               <l>I wyll beware, and afore prouyde</l>
               <l>That of no fouler I wyll no more betaked</l>
               <l>From their lyme twygges, I wyll flee fer a ſyde</l>
               <l>where paryll is, great paryll is to abyde</l>
               <l>Come nere thou churle, herken to my ſpeche</l>
               <l>Of thre wyſdomes that I wyll the teche</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Gyue nat of wyſdome to haſty credence</l>
               <l>To euery tale of eche tydynge</l>
               <l>But conſydre of reaſon and prudence</l>
               <l>Amonge many tales, is many a great leſynge</l>
               <l>Haſty credence, hath cauſed great hynderynge</l>
               <l>Reporte of tales &amp; tydynges brought vp newe</l>
               <l>Cauſed many a man, to beholde vntrewe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e parte take this of my raunſon</l>
               <l>Lerne the ſeconde, grounded on ſcrypture</l>
               <l>Deſyre thou nat by no condycion</l>
               <l>thynge, which is impoſſible to recure</l>
               <l>worl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly deſyre ſtand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in auenture</l>
               <l>As who deſyreth, to clym hye on lofte</l>
               <l>By ſodeyne turne, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alleth vnſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>the thyrde is this beware both euyn and morowe</l>
               <l>Forget it nat, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e this of me</l>
               <l>For treaſour loſt, make neuer to great ſorowe</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10200:6"/>Which in no wyſe, may recouered be</l>
               <l>For who ſo taketh ſorow, for loue of any degre</l>
               <l>Reken his loue and after his payne</l>
               <l>And of one ſorowe, he maketh ſorowes twayne</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>After this leſſon, the byrde began a ſonge</l>
               <l>Of her eſcape greatly reioyſynge</l>
               <l>And ſhe remembred alſo the great wronge</l>
               <l>Done by the churle, firſte at her takinge</l>
               <l>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> her afray, and her empryſoninge</l>
               <l>Glad that ſhe was out of drede</l>
               <l>Sayd vnto hym, houerynge aboue his hede</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou were quod ſhe a naturall fole</l>
               <l>To ſuffre me departe of lewdeneſſe</l>
               <l>thou ought to complaynt and make dole</l>
               <l>And in thy herte to haue great heuyneſſe</l>
               <l>That thou loſt ſo paſſynge great rycheſſe</l>
               <l>which myght ſuffyce by value in rekenynge</l>
               <l>To pay the raunſon, of a myghty kynge</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There is a ſtone which is called a Iaconn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Of golde engendred in myn entraile</l>
               <l>which of fyne golde, paſſeth a great ounce</l>
               <l>Cytryne of colour lyke a granet of entayle</l>
               <l>which maketh men vyctoryous in batayle</l>
               <l>And who ſo euer bereth on him this ſtone</l>
               <l>Is fully aſſured agaynſt his mortall fone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>who that hath this ſtone in poſſeſſyon:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10200:6"/>Shall ſuffre no pouertye ne no indygence</l>
               <l>But of all treaſour, haue plente and foyſon</l>
               <l>And euery man ſhall do him reuerence</l>
               <l>And none enemy ſhall do to hym offence</l>
               <l>But fro thy handes, now that I am gone</l>
               <l>Playne yf thou wylt, for thy part is none</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>It cauſeth loue, and maketh men gracyous</l>
               <l>And fauourable in euery mannes ſyght</l>
               <l>It maketh acorde, bytwene men Enuyous</l>
               <l>It co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forteth ſorofull, it maketh heuy hertes lyght</l>
               <l>Lyke to poyſon in colour ſhyneth bryght</l>
               <l>I am a fole to tell all at ones</l>
               <l>Or to teche a churle, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> precious ſtones</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Men ſhulde nat put a precyous margaryte</l>
               <l>As rubyes ſaphyres, and other ſtones Inde</l>
               <l>Emeraudes, nor rounde perles white</l>
               <l>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore rude ſwyne that loue draffe of kynde</l>
               <l>For a ſowe delyteth as I fynde</l>
               <l>More in foule draffe her pygges for to glade</l>
               <l>Than in all the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry, that cometh of garnerd</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Eche thynge draweth to his ſemblable</l>
               <l>Fyſſhe in the ſee, beeſtes on the grounde</l>
               <l>The ayre for foules is mooſt comendable</l>
               <l>And to the ploughe man to tyl the lande</l>
               <l>And a churle to haue a mucforke in hande</l>
               <l>I leſe my time, any more to tary</l>
               <l>Or to teche a churle of the lapydary</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10200:7"/>
               <l>That thou haddeſt, thou getteſt no more a geyne</l>
               <l>thy lyme twygges and thy panters I defye</l>
               <l>To let me go, thou were foule ouerſene</l>
               <l>to leſe thy rycheſſe, only of foly</l>
               <l>I am nowe fre to ſynge and to fle</l>
               <l>where that my lyſte, he is a fole at all</l>
               <l>that goeth at large, and maketh hymſelfe a thrall</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To here of wyſdome thyne eares ben defe</l>
               <l>Lyke to an aſſe, that lyſteneth to an harpe</l>
               <l>Thou mayſt go pype, in a rue lefe</l>
               <l>For better it is to ſynge on thornes ſharpe</l>
               <l>than in a cage, with a churle to carpe</l>
               <l>For it was ſayd of folkes longe a gone</l>
               <l>that a churles byrde, is often wo be gone</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The churle felt his hert atwayne</l>
               <l>For very ſorow, and a ſonder ryue</l>
               <l>Alas quod he, I may well wepe and playne</l>
               <l>As a wretch neuer lyke to thryue</l>
               <l>But to mourne in pouertye all my lyue</l>
               <l>For of foly, and of wylfulneſſe</l>
               <l>I haue loſt hoyly all my rycheſſe.</l>
               <l>¶ I was a lorde I cryed out on fortune</l>
               <l>And had great treaſour late in my kepynge</l>
               <l>which myght haue made me longe to contynue</l>
               <l>with that ſtone to haue lyued lyke a kynge</l>
               <l>Or yf that I had ſet it in a rynge</l>
               <l>Borne it vpon me, I haue good ynoughe</l>
               <l>Me neded no more, to haue gene to the ploughe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:10200:7"/>
               <l>whan the byrde harde the churle thus mourne</l>
               <l>And how that he was heuy of his chere</l>
               <l>She toke her flyght, and gan agayne returne</l>
               <l>towarde hym and ſayd as ye ſhall here</l>
               <l>¶ O thou dull churle wyſdom for to lere</l>
               <l>that I the taught, all is lefte behynde</l>
               <l>Raced away and clene out of thy mynde</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Taught I the nat this wyſdome in ſentence</l>
               <l>To euery tale brought vp of newe</l>
               <l>Nat to haſtely to gyue credence</l>
               <l>Vnto the tyme, thou know that it be true</l>
               <l>All is nat golde, that ſheweth goldyſſhe hewe</l>
               <l>Nor ſtones all, by nature as I fynde</l>
               <l>Be nat ſaphyres, that ſhewe colours ynde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In this doctryne I haue loſt my labour</l>
               <l>To teche the ſuch prouerbes of ſubſtaunce</l>
               <l>Here mayſt thouſe, thy lewde blynde errour</l>
               <l>For all my body peyſed in a balaunce</l>
               <l>weyeth nat an ounſe, rude is thy remmebraunce</l>
               <l>I to haue more peyſe cloſed in myne entrayle</l>
               <l>Than all my body, ſet to the contertayle</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All my body weyeth not an vnce</l>
               <l>How myght I than haue in me a ſtone</l>
               <l>That peyſeth more than doth a great Iacou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</l>
               <l>thy brayne is dull, thy wyt is almoſte gone</l>
               <l>Of thre wyſdomes thou haſt forgotten one</l>
               <l>For thou ſhuldeſt not after my ſentence</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10200:8"/>To euery tale, gyue to haſty credente.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I bade alſo beware, both euyn and morowe</l>
               <l>For thynge loſt, by ſoden auenture</l>
               <l>thou ſholdeſt not make to moche ſorowe</l>
               <l>whan thou ſeeſt, thou mayſt it nat recure</l>
               <l>And there thou fayleſt that thou doſt thy buſy cure</l>
               <l>In thy ſnare to catche me agayne</l>
               <l>Thou art a fole, thy labour is in vayne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In the thyrde, thou doſt alſo raue</l>
               <l>For I bade, thou ſholdeſt in no wyſe</l>
               <l>Couete thynge, which thou mayſt nat haue</l>
               <l>In whiche thou haſt forgotten myn empryſe</l>
               <l>Thus I may ſay, playnly to deuyſe</l>
               <l>that thou haſt of madneſſe forgotten all thre</l>
               <l>Notable wyſdomes, that I taught the</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>It were foly, more with the to carpe</l>
               <l>Or preche of wyſdome more or laſſe</l>
               <l>I holde hym mad, that bryngeth forthe an harpe</l>
               <l>Theron to teche a rude dull aſſe</l>
               <l>And madder is he, that ſyngeth to a fole a maſſe</l>
               <l>And he is moſt mad, that doth his buſyneſſ:</l>
               <l>To teche a churle, termes of gentylneſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſemblably, in Aprill and in May</l>
               <l>when gentyll byrdes make moſt melody</l>
               <l>The cuckow ſyngeth but on laye</l>
               <l>Of other tunes ſhe hath no fantaſy</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10200:8"/>Thus euery thynge, as bokes ſpecifye</l>
               <l>As foules and beſtes of euery age.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>From whens they came they take talage</l>
               <l>The Vintener treateth of his holſome wynes</l>
               <l>Of gentyll frutes boſtteth the Gardener</l>
               <l>The Fiſſher caſteth his hokes and his lyens</l>
               <l>to catche fyſſhe, in euery freſſhe ryuer</l>
               <l>Of tylthe of lande, treateth the Labourer</l>
               <l>the Gentylman, treateth of gentrye</l>
               <l>And the Churle delyteth him all in rybandry.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All one to thee, a Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kon as a Kyfe</l>
               <l>As good an Owle as a Popingay</l>
               <l>A donghyll ducke, as daynty as a Snyte</l>
               <l>Who ſerueth a churle, hath many a carefull daye</l>
               <l>A due ſyr Churle, fare well I flye my way</l>
               <l>For I caſt me neuer henſforth in my likynge</l>
               <l>A fore a churle, any more to ſynge.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ye folke that ſhall this fable ſe or rede</l>
               <l>Newe forged tales I counſeyle you to fle</l>
               <l>For loſſe of gooddes, take neuer to great hede</l>
               <l>Nor be nat ſory for none aduerſyte</l>
               <l>Nor couete thinge, that may not recouered be</l>
               <l>And remembre where euer ye gone</l>
               <l>That a churles byrde, is euer wo begonne</l>
               <l>¶ Vnto my purpoſe, this proued is fully ryue</l>
               <l>Rede and reporte by olde remembraunce</l>
               <l>That a churles byrde and a knaues wyſe</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10200:9"/>Haue oftentymes, great ſorow and myſchaunce</l>
               <l>And who that hath fredome, hath all ſuffyſaunce</l>
               <l>For better is fredome, with lytel in gladneſſe</l>
               <l>Than to be thrall, with all worldly rycheſſe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To lytell queyer, and recommende me</l>
               <l>Vnto my mayſter, with humble affection</l>
               <l>Beſechynge hym lowly of mercy and pyte</l>
               <l>Of this rude makynge, to take compaſſyon</l>
               <l>And as touchynge the tranſlacion</l>
               <l>Out of frenche, how it engliſſhed be</l>
               <l>All thynge is ſayd vnder correction</l>
               <l>with ſupportacyon, of your benygnite.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprented at London in Lothburi ouer againſt Sainct Margarytes church by me Wyliam Copland.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:10200:9"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
